Liang Yi.
梁翊
It's too stuffy.
闷死我了 梁翊
Stay still.
头别动
It's suffocating.
憋死我了
Are you okay?
你没事吧
What about me?
还有我呢 还有我呢
Calm down.
别急
Turn over.
转过来
I live comfortably for several decades
想不到我风光数载
and now, this is my end.
如今却落得这般下场
How unjust!
我亏死了呀我
Seriously though,
说认真的
is there a secret passage here?
这里有没有出去的密道啊
This is my Chinese alchemy room.
这是我的炼丹室
There's no secret passage whatsoever.
要什么密道啊
Stop fiddling around.
你们俩都别找了
There's only one exit
这里只有一个出口
and it can only be opened by the entrance.
而且这个出口只能从入口打开
I didn't know they would do this to me.
我哪知道他们会这么对我
You have no idea.
你们有所不知
I spend a long time concocting pills here.
每次我在这儿闭关炼丹都要好久
I am utterly devoted
对圣上的龙体
to His Majesty's health.
我那是煞费苦心啊
Now that they left me here,
你们说 现在他们这么对我
they should be called mentor killers,
是不是欺师灭祖
they should be viewed as lowly scums.
是不是禽兽不如
Lingzheng, you ingrate!
灵正 你这个乌龟王八蛋
I curse you!
我咒你死
He looks educated but is actually a simpleton.
看似精明 其实就是个草包啊
Your arm.
你的手臂
It's fine.
小意思 没事
What are you doing?
你要干吗
You're injured because of me. I should take care of your wound.
大人为我受伤 我为大人包扎
It's only right.
应当应分
Don't.
别 别 别
Don't move.
别动
Didn't you say
大人不是说了吗
that I'm one of your own?
我是你的人
Excuse me.
两位 打扰一下
Since we're all stuck down here anyway,
既然我们都被关在这里
would you care to drink with me?
那是否有兴趣共饮此酒
No thanks.
不用了
Great.
太好了
What should we do?
咱们该怎么办
Are we really stuck here forever?
难不成真的要一直困在这儿
Didn't you hear what the Grand Preceptor said?
没听到国师说吗
There's no other exit.
没有出口了
And you'll give up like that?
你就不再想想办法
Let's brainstorm then.
一起想喽
What are you doing, Miss?
姑娘 你到底要干吗呀
It's just a stone wall,
这里只是实墙
not a metal wall.
又不是铜墙铁壁
We can dig our way out.
想必可以挖得出去
But the wall is thick.
墙这么厚
When a woman like you finishes digging,
你个女娃娃挖出去
we'll be already dead from starvation.
我们早都饿死了
Better than being sitting ducks.
那也总好过坐以待毙
Excuse me.
这位军爷
When will Lord Liang return?
你们梁大人
Mr. Qin. I will inform you once Lord Liang returns.
秦小爷 大人回来定会告诉你
If you can't stay here,
如果等不及
you can return home first.
还是先回府吧
Where did he bring Qiu Yan to?
他把秋嫣到底带到哪儿去了
I have no news whatsoever. How can I return home like this?
音讯全无 这我怎么回
Where's Song Jin? Bring me to Song Jin.
宋锦呢 带我去找宋锦也可以
Freeze!
所有人都待在原地 不许动
Sir, you're...
官爷 你们这是
I'm from the Firewood Office.
劈柴处办案
Where's the Head here?
老鸨呢
I have been looking for her too.
我也找半天了
Sir Jin, I have searched everywhere.
锦爷 前前后后都搜遍了
No trace of Lord Liang and Miss Qiu Yan.
没有看见大人和秋嫣姑娘
Check if there's any secret passage.
给我找找有没有秘密地道
Now!
继续搜
Yes, sir.
是 搜
Stop digging.
别挖了
You'll exhaust yourself to death.
不然死了之后也是饿死鬼
I wiggled out
我好不容易
of He Feng's death trap.
才从贺沣的棺材里面爬出来
Before I can even enjoy my freedom,
还没活成个人样
I have to meet my end in another death trap?
我就要死在这口棺材里
No way.
我不服
Life and death are just a matter of seconds.
生死啊 也就是一瞬间的事情
You don't have a say in it.
从来没有什么道理可讲
When the Yamla comes for your soul,
阎王爷打勾时啊
your consent is none of his concern.
从来不会在乎你服不服
Please, no need to be so nonchalant.
你少装洒脱
Are you willing to die here
就为查个假银票
for your fake notes investigation?
你就要死在这里 你就甘心
This is my job.
我是干这个的
If my journey ends here, it ends at the right place.
死在这里也是死得其所
I won't accept this.
我不甘心
I haven't had a good day before.
我还没过过一天舒坦日子呢
Why should I die here?
凭什么要我死在这儿
Ever since I left the He Residence,
我从贺家回来的时候我就想
I told myself that now that I survived,
我既然好不容易活下来
I had to live every day to the fullest.
我就要过好每一天
I want to show those who wish me death
我要过得比他们好
how well I am enjoying my life now.
我让那些想我死的人好好看看
My life
我这个命啊
is more tenacious than they imagined.
比他们想得要金贵
If you didn't lie to me,
你若不是骗我
you wouldn't end up like this.
也不会落到如此境地
Is Qin Xuan worth
就是为了嫁给秦暄
the trouble?
值得吗
You think I did everything
你以为我做这一切
to marry Qin Xuan?
就是为了嫁给秦暄
Instead of being married to someone else,
比起嫁谁
I want to walk my own path.
我更想自己选择我要走的路
I don't want anyone to tell me what to do.
而不是别人替我选
If you can get out of here and do whatever you want,
那如果能活下去让你自己选择
what will you do?
你想做什么
I heard many stories
我听说过不少
about dead women who were falsely accused in their household.
宅院里冤死女子的故事
I want to right their names.
我想替她们申冤
I will jot down their stories and publish a compilation
把每个案子记录在册 写成话本
to warn future women.
警戒后人
You live most of your life in the comfort of your house.
我说你久在深闺
Why are you so interested in strange cases?
为何对冤案奇闻这么感兴趣
When I was little, I was illiterate
我小时候不大识字
but I wanted to read.
可我又想读书
To indulge me,
我母亲为了培养我的兴趣
my mother let me read stories of criminal cases.
就让我读公案话本
The first book I read was an incomplete hand-written copy.
记得最早我看的是半卷手抄
I think it's called Collection of Odd Occurrences.
那名字叫 叫大朔奇案录
I was kept in my house
我虽身在宅院之间
but my mind followed the law enforcer in the book.
可我的心就好像跟着书里的刑名
We solved cases, revealed the truth,
一同破凶案 查真相
punished the evil, and restored peace together.
除鬼魅 安社稷
Thanks to that incomplete book,
也就是因为那半卷书
I learned to recognize characters.
我才把字认得七七八八的
So you want to be a law enforcer.
原来是想做刑名啊
Fine, I'll pray for you
行 那我就替你许愿
so that the God
让老天保佑你
will make you into a man in your next life.
下辈子做个男人
No, I'm fine with being a woman.
不 我要做女人
I believe one day,
我相信终有一天
men and women will be equal.
天底下的女子也会像男子一样
We can study, work as government officials,
读书 做官
open business or shop,
经商 开店
or do whatever we want.
做任何自己想做的事情
Even though this probably won't happen in my lifetime,
哪怕这一世我看不到
for my next life or the life after that,
下一世 下下世
I still want to be a woman
我也要身为女人
and watch it happen with my eyes.
看到那天的来临
No rebuttal from you today?
今天居然一句都不驳
That's not like you at all.
不像你啊
Let those who are about to die
将死之人
say their piece.
不值一驳
What about you?
那你呢
What do you want to do?
那你想做什么
I don't think
我总觉得
you're content doing the government's bidding all your life.
你不会一心只想做个朝廷鹰犬
Song Jin.
宋锦
When I grow up, my brush will be my sword.
将来我要以笔为剑
I will use my brush
用手中笔
to detail all the injustice in this world.
书尽天下鬼魅魍魉不公之事
I will rid all evil and maintain peace.
除宵小 安社稷
Just like my father.
就像我父亲那样
(Do not hold grudges again anyone else.)
永远不要记恨任何人
(I just want you to lead a peaceful life.)
为父只望你能平安逍遥一生
This is the last thing the Marquis left you.
这是老侯爷留给您最后的东西
His letter does not mean anything to me.
这封信留着对我没有任何的意义
I cannot forgive
我做不到不恨
nor do I plan to.
我也不想做到
As I said,
我说过
my duty lies with the Firewood Office.
劈柴处办案 职责所在而已
It's just a way for me to achieve great success.
我干这个就是为了升官发财
That's all.
没有别的
When you said you wanted to leave the Imperial Park,
起初你提要离开禁苑的时候
I thought you were afraid of the powerful
我的确以为你又同贺家一案一般
like you were dealing with the case of He family.
惧怕权贵
But now, you would rather die here
可你宁愿死在这里
than concede to Lingzheng.
都不与掌教妥协
That means even though you're a clout-chaser,
这说明你虽然追权求势
you still have your own principles.
可心里还是有底线跟原则的
What?
怎么了
If you're too exhausted to run later,
待会儿要是没力气逃跑
don't blame me for leaving you here.
别怪我不管你啊
You found a way out?
你想到脱身的办法了
This is sulfur.
这是硫黄
It's as heavy as the weight.
和砝码相同的重量
Niter.
硝石
Carbon powder.
碳粉
Your way out is pill concoction?
你说的法子是炼丹药啊
If you combine the three of them
这三样东西啊
on a specific ratio,
按照一定比例混合在一起
you get what we call, black powder.
就是俗称的黑火药
Follow me.
跟我来
Touch this wall.
来摸摸这堵墙
It's cold.
怎么凉凉的
Behind it is the sacred lake of the Imperial Park.
这背后就是禁苑圣湖
Judging from the route they took
从我们被押来炼丹室
to send us to this Chinese alchemy room,
行走的方位来判断
we are actually closer to the sacred lake now.
我们刚才一直在接近圣湖
This cold wall confirms my hypothesis.
受潮的墙点就能印证这一点
And judging from its temperature,
而且按照受潮的程度来看
the wall isn't very thick.
这墙体并不特别厚
If we can make a hole here,
只要炸开这一个点
the lake water will burst this wall down.
湖水啊 就能冲垮这堵墙
But we don't have a fuse.
可是咱们没有引线
If we detonate the bomb in close quarter,
如果近距离点燃
it will backfire.
会炸到我们自己的
What should we do then?
你想呢
I have a solution.
我有办法了
What's up?
怎么了
- Go. Go. Hurry. - Are we
走走走 快快快 这是
in hell now?
到阎王殿了
If you don't sober up now, you will be.
你再不醒啊 真快到了
I...
这
I'm doomed anyway.
我都快要死了
Save some for me, at least.
你倒是给我留点啊
Chinese alchemy room.
炼丹室
Follow me!
跟我来
You two, stay here. The rest, follow me.
你们两个留下 其他人跟我走
Hurry!
快
Come.
走
Are you okay?
你没事吧
Do not tell anyone
方才的事情
what happened just now.
你不能告诉任何人
What?
什么呀
Don't you have faith in your Qin Xuan?
你不是相信你的秦暄吗
This is different. It's...
这不一样 这 这是
It's...
这是
Come on. I saved you.
救了你还这么多废话
I owe you my life.
我欠了大人一命
I will repay you in the future.
日后定当偿还
All right.
行了 行了
Let's go.
快走吧
What's this?
这什么呀
Golden handcuffs given by the Tocharians.
这吐火罗密贡的金丝手梏
The only pair in the world.
整个大朔就这么一件
Do you have the key? Open it.
有钥匙吗 快把它打开啊
I don't mean to bother
二位 打扰一下
but I see someone armed coming here.
那边好像有人拿着刀过来了
What should we do?
我们该怎么办呀
They are over there. After them!
他们在那边 快 快追
Run!
走 走 走
Stand there!
站住
The key fell into the water.
钥匙掉水里了
No time for that. Just run.
管不了那么多了 走
Stand there!
站住
Don't run.
别跑
Run.
快走
Hurry up.
快 快 快
Stand there!
站住 站住
Don't let them escape!
别让他们跑了
- Stay there. - Don't run.
别跑 站住
Hurry.
快
Stand there!
站住 站住
This way.
这边
Don't run. Capture them!
别跑 抓住他们
Run.
快走
Capture them.
快抓住他们
Stay still.
都别动
Darn you!
混账
Lingzheng. Xuanjing.
灵正 玄静
You traitors.
你们两个混账东西
You deceived your mentor. You're inhumane.
你们欺师灭祖 丧尽天良
Have you no fear of God's wrath?
你们不怕遭天谴吗你们
Hurry.
快
Is your leg okay?
脚没事吧
You kicked me. Run.
还不是被你踹的 快跑
Quick.
快 快 快
How quickly can they come here?
他们多久会来
Soon.
应该不久
Look at this, you two.
你们两个
Lord Liang
我们梁大人
is summoning backup now.
已经开始召集人马了
Don't you want to kill us?
你们不是要杀我们吗
We will wait for you here.
我们三个人现在就按兵不动
Come kill us if you can.
有本事 来来来
Come kill me.
你来 你来杀我呀
They are gone.
他们走了
We didn't find anyone, sir.
大人 没有
How can two living beings disappear just like that?
这么两个大活人 怎么能不见了
Sir, someone saw the red signal.
大人 有人看见红烟信号
Northwest from here. 20 li away.
西北方向 二十里远
All of you, come with me.
所有人都跟我来
Come.
走
Gather everyone.
快召集所有人马
Yes, sir.
是
Are Liang Yi and Qiu Yan in danger?
是不是梁翊秋嫣有危险
Bring me along.
带我一起去
Come.
走
What?
干吗
What are you doing?
你们这是要干什么
They are lighting the firewood.
他们在点火 怎么办呀
Lingzheng.
灵正
How dare you use such a lowly trick
你居然用如此卑劣的手段
on us?
谋害我们
You have no shame.
简直是卑鄙无耻啊你
I...
这 这
What should we do?
怎么办
We can't go down.
下不去
Take this, Qiu Yan.
秋嫣 拿着
Thanks.
多谢 多谢 多谢
Stop tearing. We don't have time.
不撕了 没时间了
Cover your mouth.
捂住嘴 捂住嘴
(Hongzhen Holy Palace) The Imperial Park of Hongzhen Sect.
弘真门禁苑
We don't have much time now.
时间紧迫 管不了这么多了
Let's go.
走
All trespassers will be beheaded.
擅闯禁苑者 立斩不
Over here. Rescue them.
这边 救人
Qin Xuan. We're here!
秦暄 我们在这里
Don't worry, Qiu Yan.
秋嫣 别害怕
I'm coming to save you.
马上来救你
Charge!
杀
Excuse me.
两位 打扰一下
Are they Lord Liang's people?
楼 楼下可是梁大人的兵马
Yes.
是 是 是
Upstairs now!
跟我上楼
Sir Jin.
锦爷
Back off now.
往后退
Sir!
爷
What are you doing?
你要干吗
Follow me. Hug me tight.
跟着我就是 抱紧我
Are you ready?
准备好了吗
Don't be afraid. Here we go.
不用害怕 走了
Are you okay?
你没事吧
Yes.
没事
Thank you for saving me.
多谢搭救 多谢搭救
Qiu Yan. Are you okay?
秋嫣 没事吧
Qin Xuan, how do you know we're here?
秦暄 你怎么知道我们在这儿
Sir. Sorry, I'm late.
爷 我来迟了
Your wound...
你这伤口
I'm fine.
我没事
I focused too much on rescuing you.
是我心急救人
The head of Hongzhen Sect died.
掌教没留活口
You did the right thing.
你做得没错
Let's talk once we're back.
我们回去再说吧
Bring them back first.
先拿人
Come.
走吧
Bring all of them back.
全部带走
All of you, bring them back.
所有人 带走
Come. Get up.
走 起来
Come.
走 走 走
Hurry.
走 快点
Careful.
小心
Qin Xuan.
秦暄
Are you all right?
还好吧
I just killed someone for the first time.
这是我第一次杀人
Qiu Yan. Check Mr. Tao Zhugong.
秋嫣 陶朱公
He is not the assassin who killed Xiao Tie.
陶朱公不是射杀肖铁的刺客
The crossbow is on his right arm
他用的是右手臂弩
while the one who killed Xiao Tie shot with his left arm.
而射杀肖铁的刺客是左手臂弩
So Xiao Tie's assassin
这么说刺杀肖铁之人
is someone else.
另有其人
They still slipped away.
终究还是有漏网之鱼
Treacherous disciples!
你们这帮逆徒啊
Did I not treat you kindly enough?
为师平时怎么对你们的
(Guangmei Hall) All of you betrayed me
关键时刻一个一个
- the moment it mattered. - My lord.
全都背叛我 大人
- You are still alive. - The audacity, all of you.
你还真是命大 全都背叛我
Sir, they almost killed me.
大人 他们险些要杀了我
Fortunately, the officials came in time to save me.
幸得官爷及时相救
Why are the Imperial Guards here?
禁军怎么来了
(Guangmei Hall) Did I not give you everything?
哪一样不是为师给你们的
Seems like we have gotten the Imperial Court's attention.
看来此事已经惊动了宫中
How should we answer to His Majesty?
圣上面前你我如何答对啊
We can't hide it anymore. Let's come clean.
瞒是瞒不住了 如实禀报吧
Okay.
好
Greetings, Grand Preceptor.
见过国师
His Majesty was shocked to learn a fire broke out in the Imperial Park.
皇上惊闻禁苑走水
I was sent here to investigate.
特命我带人前来查看
Why are you here too, Lord Liang?
怎么梁大人也在此
My cunning disciple instigated an insurgence.
逆徒灵正带人作乱
Fortunately, Lord Liang intervened in time.
幸得梁大人急时相救
The disciples have all been apprehended.
眼下逆徒已悉数服法
A fire within the Imperial Park is a serious matter.
禁苑纵火 兹事体大
Grand Preceptor, please enter the palace with me
还请国师速与我入宫
and explain to His Majesty.
亲自面圣解释
As for the traitors the Grand Preceptor mentioned...
至于国师所说的这些反叛之人
Come forth.
来人哪
Tie them down and carry them away.
悉数绑了 一并带走
Imperial Commander Yan.
闫殿帅
Other than an insurgence,
这些逆贼除了犯上作乱
these criminals are also involved
还牵涉到劈柴处
in a fake notes fraud the Firewood Office is investigating.
正在追查的一桩假银票案
Can you hand them over to the Firewood Office?
可否交于劈柴处
Lord Liang, His Majesty wants to handle this matter himself.
梁大人 此事圣上已亲自过问
Perhaps we can keep them
不如交于我们
and let His Majesty decide later?
留等圣上亲自处决
What do you think, Lord Liang?
梁大人意下如何呀
How scrupulous of you, Imperial Commander Yan.
闫殿帅思虑周全
Oh,
对了
this girl is a maid in Wanyan House.
不过这个小姑娘是万艳楼的侍女
She's not related to the case at all.
与此案无关
She was merely a guide to bring us here.
因为帮助我们寻路 跟随此地
Please allow me
还请闫殿帅允许
to see her back.
让我送她回去
Lord Liang is telling the truth.
梁大人所言非虚
This lady here does not work in this Imperial Park.
小姑娘确实不是我禁苑中人
It's just a trivial matter. You decide, Lord Liang.
此等小事 梁大人自便
See you, Grand Preceptor.
国师 请
Lord Liang.
梁大人
I will not forget what you did today.
救护之情 没齿难忘
It is my duty.
不必挂心
Come. Bring them away.
来人哪 带走
He can switch his mood so quickly.
他这个人怎么变脸比翻书还快
As if
仿佛刚才那个
he wasn't the lousy drunkard
抱着酒坛醉生梦死的人
from just now.
不是他似的
The Six Ministries with their respective ministers are all like this.
六部九卿这样的人多得是
What he was saying is
他的意思是
the Imperial Guards
万艳楼那边
will take care of those people in the Wanyan House too.
估计禁军的人也会接管
Song Jin, did you locate their treasury
宋锦 昨晚搜查时候
in your search last night?
有没有找到他们的金库
Yes, sir.
爷 找到了
But we couldn't find the ledger.
只是尚未找到交易名册
When I stole the fake note,
我之前偷拿假银票的时候
I came across this small book
曾看见过一本小册子
with tons of names
里面密密麻麻记了一些
and dates on it.
人名和日期
Ping'er. Where is the book now?
萍儿 那本册子现在何处
My father should have it.
应该在我爹爹那儿
As well as the other fake notes that aren't used yet.
还有一些我偷来没花掉的假银票
Let's head to Wanyan House with Ping'er
那咱们赶紧跟萍儿去万艳楼
before the Imperial Guards seal that place.
趁禁军还未查封
Qiu Yan.
秋嫣
This is...
你这是
I'll explain to you later.
我回头再跟你解释
Let me tag along.
那我跟你们一起去吧
Mr. Qin.
秦小爷
My Master is there for serious business.
我家爷是去办公务
We should wait for them in the Firewood Office.
咱们还是先回劈柴处等着吧
I only trust them too.
我只信哥哥姐姐
Qin Xuan, you should head back with Song Jin.
秦暄 那你还是跟宋锦先回去吧
Lord Liang and I will be back soon.
我跟梁大人很快就回来
Wait for us in the Firewood Office.
在劈柴处等我们
Be careful.
那你千万小心
Let's go.
快走吧
I'll wait for you in the Firewood Office.
我在劈柴处等你
Okay.
好
Father.
爹
Ping'er!
萍儿
- Father! - Ping'er!
爹爹 萍儿
Oh, my Ping'er.
萍儿啊萍儿
Where were you last night?
你昨天晚上到哪儿去了
Many officers surrounded Wanyan House yesterday.
昨晚哪 官爷围了万艳楼
I was looking for you everywhere.
我四处找你啊
Father, I...
爹爹 我
When I was stealing some fake notes yesterday,
我昨天偷假银票的时候
I bumped into these two officers from the Firewood Office.
撞见了劈柴处的两位大人
They said they would pardon me.
大人说不追究我
(Wanyan House) Greetings, officers.
小人见过二位大人
Thank you for giving my daughter another chance.
多谢二位大人饶了小女一命啊
Save that for later.
先不忙谢
I heard from your daughter
听您闺女说
that you kept the fake notes she stole?
她偷的假银票都是归您收着
Indeed.
是 是 是
The fake notes are all in my abode.
假银票都在小人的住处
I will show them to you now.
小人这就带二位大人去取
Ping'er.
萍儿
A client from yesterday
昨天啊 有客人
gave us some delicacies from Daoyu Pastry.
赏给爹爹稻御坊的点心
I know you like them a lot
爹爹知道你最喜欢吃
so I save them for you.
都给你留着呢
Come with me, officers.
大人这边走
Inside, please.
二位大人 里面请
The living place of a servant.
下人住的地方
Please don't mind it, officers.
二位大人可莫要嫌弃啊
Please give me a moment.
二位大人稍待
I'll retrieve the cash notes now.
我这就去取
Have a seat.
大人请坐
Have some tea.
大人 请喝茶
Thank you.
多谢
Watch out!
小心
Ping'er. Ping'er.
萍儿 萍儿
Don't, Ping'er.
萍儿 不要
Leave me be!
别管我
Ping'er.
萍儿
Father?
爹
Father.
爹爹
Who are you?
你到底是什么人
Your sworn enemy.
和你不共戴天的仇人
I don't even know you.
我们素不相识
Did we cross paths?
有什么仇
Huizhou Magistrate, Dou Ying.
惠州知府窦英
He was killed because you framed him.
遭你构陷丧命
Do you remember him?
你可记得
I investigated many officials.
我办过的官不计其数
This does not jog my memory.
我已经忘记了
I will never forget that
可我永远不会忘
because Dou Ying was my father.
窦英是我爹爹
Sir, I searched everywhere.
爷 都搜过了
He must be the bodyguard who saved you.
他就是救下你的那个护院吧
A crossbow on his left arm.
左手臂弩
He must be Xiao Tie's assassin.
看来他就是杀死肖铁之人
What is Lingzheng to you two?
你们二人和灵正什么关系
Why did he do Lingzheng's bidding?
他又为何替灵正行凶
We wandered to the Capital.
我们一路流落至京
We had no shelter and no food.
无依无靠 食不饱腹
I'm good at drawing
我从小擅画
so I devoted myself to forging fake notes.
便挖空心思 想画些假银票
Unfortunately, Mr. Lingzheng found out.
不料被掌教大人撞见
Young girl.
小小年纪
How dare you scam me with fake notes?
竟然用假银票来骗我
Follow me to the court.
走 跟我见官去
- Mister. - Come!
老板 走
I'll pay for her buns.
她的馒头钱我付了
Thanks, sir.
谢谢大人 谢谢大人
- Thanks, sir. - All right.
谢谢大人 好 好嘞好嘞
Fresh buns!
馒头啊
You drew this?
这你画的
(Heng Gui Banknotes, Five Taels) He said I was talented
掌教说我颇有天赋
so he hired Xiao Tie to tutor me.
便找来肖铁教我 辅助我
My bodyguard was good at fighting.
叔叔颇擅拳脚
To protect me,
为了我
he did Lingzheng's bidding.
便替掌教卖命
He hid you two in Wanyan House.
他将你们二人藏在万艳楼
A perfect hiding place,
可谓是神不知鬼不觉
I must say.
好算计
I don't regret being someone's pawn.
替人卖命我不后悔
The only thing I regret
我唯一后悔的
is I failed to take your life just now.
就是刚才没有一刀取你的狗命
Liang Yi.
梁翊
You accused my father
你罗织罪名
of embezzling one million taels.
诬告我爹爹贪墨百万银两
My family is ruined because of you.
害我家破人亡
I will come back to haunt you as a ghost.
我就是做鬼也不会放过你的
Vengeance is all you can see.
你执意要报仇
Have you thought about his life?
可你想过他的死活吗
The Dou family hired him.
他死生都是我窦家的人
He would want to give his life for us.
这是他应得的
He didn't want to avenge the Dou family.
他并不想为你们窦家报仇
Otherwise, he would have killed me
不然他在刺杀肖铁的时候
when he was trying to kill Xiao Tie.
便可以直接对我动手
I think he was happy
我猜他只是想继续
being your father.
扮演好萍儿爹爹而已
I don't care.
那又如何
You said Lord Liang killed your father.
你怪他害死了你的爹爹
But you killed your other father yourself.
可你却亲手害死了你另一个爹爹
He left these snacks for you.
这个糕点是他专门留给你的
He never ever took a bite.
却未曾动过一口
You truly don't remember the Dou family's case?
你当真不记得窦家的案子了
Why do you ask?
你为何这么问
You and I are both very petty.
梁大人与我都是睚眦必报的人
By extrapolation,
推己及人
I don't think you're this forgetful.
想来大人的记性不会那么差
Year 22 of Chengzhao.
成昭二十二年
Huizhou Magistrate, Dou Ying,
惠州知府窦英
accepted bribery, sold governmental positions,
广收贿赂 倒卖官职
and embezzled public funds.
私吞库粮
(In his house, we found 10,000 taels worth of gold)
仅仅在他家中就抄得黄金万两
(500,000 taels worth of silver,)
白银五十万两
(and tens of precious objects.)
字画珍玩数十筐
(I remember every case)
我办过的每一个案子
(I solved.)
我都记得
Sir, I checked everywhere.
爷 都搜过了
If her father was guilty,
既然她父亲当真有罪
why didn't you tell her the truth?
你为何不把真相告诉她
Children
为人儿女
only see the best of their parents.
总是只能看到父母良善的一面
Why ruin that illusion for her?
又何必揭穿呢
Oh,
对了
when Ping'er was about to attack me,
刚才萍儿出手的时候
you stopped her in time.
你及时阻拦
How did you know she was about to make a move?
你是如何看出她的动机
Wanyan House is a place filled with perfume.
万艳楼浓香四溢
But the perfume Ping'er wears
而萍儿身上的香
is different from the workers there.
与姑娘们的迥而不同
The perfume pouch she carries
我留意到她身上的香囊
is from Liuxiang Perfumery in the West District.
是西城留香斋的
The perfume pouch from that place
西城留香斋的香囊
costs at least one tael
少说也得一两银子一个
and you need to buy a new one every fortnight.
且半月就要更换
Otherwise, the fragrance will fade.
否则香味不存
If Ping'er truly committed thievery
若真如萍儿所说
due to poverty,
她是因贫困盗窃
why would she carry a luxury like that then?
又怎会用此等奢靡之物
I didn't know you were that well-versed in feminine products.
想不到你还懂这些闺阁趣味
My sister, Qiu Min,
我的妹妹秋珉
is obsessed with the perfume pouch from Liuxiang Perfumery.
最喜欢留香斋的香囊
She always talks about it
她时常跟我提起
and that's why I know the subject well.
因而我就有所了解
Wait. What were you implying?
梁大人你什么意思
You think I'm not womanly enough?
你是说我不像个女子
I just want
我只是想说
to thank you.
多谢
I saved your life and you saved mine.
我救了你一命 你也救了我一命
We're even now.
咱俩两清了
Good.
甚好
Who would have thought that in one day,
谁曾想到短短一日
some might not live to see today's sunset.
好多人就再见不到今日的太阳了
This must be your first time seeing bloodshed.
你是头一回瞧见刀剑厮杀吧
It must be tough on you.
难为你了
Not at all.
谁说的
I already saw blood when I was little.
我小时候就见过
You were just a little girl.
那时候你还是黄毛丫头
Where did you see blood?
上哪儿见呢
Let's go back now
咱们还是快些回去吧
and take off the handcuffs.
赶紧把这手梏断开
Qin Xuan is waiting for us.
秦暄还等着咱们呢
Have you seen the ocean before?
你从前见过大海吗
Never.
没有
It's beautiful, isn't it?
景色不错吧
Hug me tight.
坐稳了
You're saying
你是说
that the Firewood Office barged into my imperial park,
劈柴处的人与灵正短兵相接
crossed arms with Lingzheng's people,
硬闯我禁苑
to save you and Liang Yi?
这才救了你和梁翊
It is my incompetence
臣管教无方
that allowed outsiders to barge into the Imperial Park
致使外人闯入禁苑
and destroyed the place of worship and the pills for Your Majesty.
坏了圣上的修炼和丹药
I am at fault here.
臣罪有攸归
I await my punishment.
请圣上发落
Lingzheng was the main culprit
既然这次作乱的是灵正
and he has been captured.
他已伏诛
God has preserved justice.
可见天意昭昭
Since God has delivered the judgment,
天罚了
I shouldn't.
我就不罚了
You have been in shock for half a day.
你已受惊半日
Go back and rest.
回去好好将息
Discipline your disciples well too.
也好好管管你那些徒子徒孙
It's fine if my pills are destroyed.
坏了我的药不要紧
But if we disturb God,
若扰了神仙清净
and God decides to punish our subjects,
降罪于万民
it will be too great a sin for both of us.
你我都担不起呀
Understood, Your Majesty.
谢圣上隆恩
Dismissed.
下去吧
Yes, Your Majesty.
是
Your Majesty,
圣上
do we let the Firewood Office
后面的案子
see the follow-up through?
是否还交由劈柴处去审哪
Have you found that someone
前几日我让你找的人
I asked you to?
到了吗
Yes, Your Majesty.
到了 圣上
Done.
好了
Why break the chain?
为何只是砸开
Is there no key that can open the handcuffs?
这手梏没有钥匙解开吗
Tocharian Golden Handcuffs have a sophisticated design.
吐火罗金丝手梏啊 设计紧密
You cannot replicate the key.
钥匙无法复制
Breaking it open by force
强行打开
will only cause injuries.
只会伤到肌肤
The Firewood Office doesn't have a spare key?
你们劈柴处也没有备用钥匙
The Tocharians only gave us one.
吐火罗进贡只有这一把
If we want the key to open it,
想要取钥匙
we need a Tocharian blacksmith.
还需要找到吐火罗工匠才行
You're saying
你这意思
that we need to send someone to the Tarim Basin to find a blacksmith?
还要派人去吐火罗找工匠
How long will a return journey take?
那这一往一返要多久了
Around two months.
大概需要两个月吧
Sir, news from the Imperial Court.
爷 宫中消息
His Majesty assigned the fake notes
圣上把银票并禁苑的案子
and the Imperial Park case to the Main Administrative Office.
交给总章衙门负责了
The Firewood Office has been handling this case.
明明是劈柴处一直负责此案
The case can be concluded soon
如今眼看可以结案
so why hand it to someone else right now?
怎么要把案子移交给别人
I'm not surprised.
不意外
Song Jin charged into the imperial park to save me.
宋锦为了救我 带人强闯禁苑
That's a serious crime on its own.
已经犯下大忌
His Majesty did not admonish us.
圣上并没有过多怪罪
He just wants us to cease what we're doing.
只是下令我们不要再插手
So be it then.
也罢
Song Jin.
宋锦
Transfer all evidence that you found in Wanyan House's treasury
你在万艳楼金库搜到的证物
to the Main Administrative Office.
移交给总章衙门
Go now.
去吧
Wait.
等等
Can I have a look at them first?
能不能容我先看一下
If the snitch from my house bought fake notes from Wanyan House,
若我家内贼在万艳楼购得银票
he must have left a trace.
必定雁过留痕
And now,
现如今
the ledger for the fake notes is nowhere to be found.
买卖银票的交易册子下落不明
I want to see if I can
我想看看证物
find something from the evidence pile.
万一我能从当中找到些线索
Or else,
否则
today will be in vain.
我这一天就白跑了
So much evidence here.
这么多证物
Which one belongs to the Qiu family?
哪件才是秋家的
Everything we confiscated
这里所有的押物啊
has been labeled.
都写着主人姓氏
It shouldn't be hard for you to find what you're after.
你们找找 应该不难
Who's there?
什么人
The Main Administrative Office
总章衙门
is here to collect all evidence
奉旨前来提取
regarding the Wanyan House case.
万艳楼一案相关证物